<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mmrojooo.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mmrojooo.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-02-09T11:29:56+01:00</updated><id>https://mmrojooo.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mofletes Colorados</title><subtitle>Pasión por el arte explorando nuevas perspectivas</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The Legacy of Berthe Morisot: An Intimate Look at Motherhood and Art</title><link href="https://mmrojooo.github.io/en/2024/04/24/The-Legacy-of-Berthe-Morisot-en.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Legacy of Berthe Morisot: An Intimate Look at Motherhood and Art" /><published>2024-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://mmrojooo.github.io/en/2024/04/24/The-Legacy-of-Berthe-Morisot-en</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mmrojooo.github.io/en/2024/04/24/The-Legacy-of-Berthe-Morisot-en.html"><![CDATA[<h1>The Legacy of Berthe Morisot: An Intimate Look at Motherhood and Art</h1>
<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/swPsYTYEPas?si=RX5PGNWr_QWfRkFb" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>
<p>In 1868, the exceptional Berthe Morisot wrote to her sister Edna from the depths of her being, expressing a tumult of emotions that resonated with the duality of her longings: art and motherhood. In her letter, Berthe speaks with striking frankness about her struggles and dreams, showing a steely determination to achieve her goals despite the complexities of her personal and professional situation.</p>
<div align="center"><img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/A vintage letter on an antique desk.jpeg" alt="A vintage letter on an antique desk"></div> 
<p>Berthe was born into a high bourgeois Parisian family in 1841, an environment that offered her a privileged artistic education but also confined her within conventional gender expectations. From an early age, she and her sister Edna demonstrated exceptional talent for drawing, which was even recognized by their teacher, who warned their parents of the revolutionary potential of their daughters in art, a field dominated by men.</p>

<p>Berthe's education was unusual for a woman of her time. She could not attend the academy of fine arts, so her parents hired a private tutor. This tutor, a neoclassical painter, soon recognized that her abilities surpassed the limits of conventional salon painting. He even suggested they obtain copyist licenses to study at the Louvre, a practice that greatly expanded her artistic horizon.</p>
<div align="center"><img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/An interior depiction of a 19th-century art studio where Berthe Morisot and her sister are being instructed by a teacher.jpeg" alt="A vintage letter on an antique desk"></div> 
<p>Over time, Berthe and her sister sought to advance beyond the imposed limits, which led them to learn to paint en plein air, a technique that later profoundly influenced Impressionism. They were introduced to the famous landscapist Corot, who supported them in their development, though always within the limits imposed by society on women of their class.</p>

<p>The significant advancement in Berthe's career came in 1864 when her works were admitted to the Official Salon, a historic achievement that marked a before and after for women in art. However, it was her participation in the first Impressionist exhibition in 1874 that truly defined her trajectory, presenting works that challenged conventional norms both in technique and theme.</p>
<div align="center"><img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/Berthe_Morisot_008.jpeg" alt="A vintage letter on an antique desk"></div> 
<p>Throughout her life, Berthe struggled to balance her career and her family responsibilities. Her marriage to Eugène Manet, brother of the renowned Édouard Manet, provided a supportive environment in which she could continue to develop as an artist. Together, they explored new techniques and participated in the vibrant cultural exchange of their time.</p>

<p>Berthe's relationship with her daughter Julie, born of this marriage, was a constant source of inspiration. Julie was not only her muse but also a presence that enriched her art, bringing freshness and emotional depth that is reflected in works like "The Lake at Bois de Boulogne" and "Red-haired Girl Sitting on a Terrace". In these paintings, Morisot's technique and style evolve, showing a mastery in the handling of light and color that captures the essence of the moment.</p>
<div align="center"><img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/Berthe-morisot-red-haired-girl-sitting-on-a-veranda.Jpg" alt="A vintage letter on an antique desk"></div> 
<p>Berthe Morisot was not only a groundbreaking figure in art; she was a voice that narrated female intimacy with unprecedented authenticity and delicacy. Her ability to convey the complexity of motherhood, from tenderness to alienation, speaks of an artist who not only painted what she saw but also deeply felt.</p>

<p>At the end of her life, in a letter to her daughter Julie, Berthe expressed an eternal love that transcends time, reflecting the depth of her emotions and her enduring legacy. Berthe Morisot not only left behind an impressive body of work; she left us a vision of the world seen through the eyes of a woman who navigated and challenged the conventions of her time to follow her passion and live authentically.</p>
<div align="center"><img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/A close-up of only the two arms of Berthe Morisot as she writes a heartfelt letter.jpeg" alt="A vintage letter on an antique desk"></div> 
<p>This is the legacy of Berthe Morisot, an artist who taught us that the true beauty and depth of art come from the ability to see and capture the truth of human experience, in all its forms.</p>]]></content><author><name>Almu</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Legacy of Berthe Morisot: An Intimate Look at Motherhood and Art In 1868, the exceptional Berthe Morisot wrote to her sister Edna from the depths of her being, expressing a tumult of emotions that resonated with the duality of her longings: art and motherhood. In her letter, Berthe speaks with striking frankness about her struggles and dreams, showing a steely determination to achieve her goals despite the complexities of her personal and professional situation. Berthe was born into a high bourgeois Parisian family in 1841, an environment that offered her a privileged artistic education but also confined her within conventional gender expectations. From an early age, she and her sister Edna demonstrated exceptional talent for drawing, which was even recognized by their teacher, who warned their parents of the revolutionary potential of their daughters in art, a field dominated by men.]]></summary></entry></feed>